Have you ever wondered
if there’s a natural way
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There’s a common type of heart condition
that causes irregular heartbeats.
It’s called atrial fibrillation,
or AFib for short,
and more and more people
every year are diagnosed with it.
Today we start with the best foods to eat
and avoid to decrease our risk of AFib.
Atrial fibrillation, or Afib, is the
most common clinical arrhythmia,
meaning abnormal heart rhythm,
affecting millions of Americans,
recognized as a global public
health problem due to its
significant burden of death and
disease resulting from stroke,
heart attacks, and heart failure.
Is there any particular diet that
may help prevent or treat it?
Well, recently we learned
what not to eat.
Low-carb diets are associated
with increased risk of developing
atrial fibrillation for
a variety of reasons.
First of all, people on low-carb diets
may be eating fewer anti-inflammatory
foods like vegetables,
fruits, and whole grains.
Reducing intake of these
anti-inflammatory foods may be
one of the important mechanisms
for the risk of getting Afib.
Secondly, a low-carbohydrate diet
means increased protein
and fat consumption,
which may stimulate oxidative stress,
the formation of free radicals,
which was also demonstrated
to be associated with Afib.
Finally, the effect could result
from the increased risk
of other cardiovascular disease,
which can set you up for Afib,
and indeed, low-carb diets are
associated with an increased risk
of overall mortality, dying
from any cause, as well as
specifically dying from cardiovascular
disease and dying from cancer.
Dietary recommendations for patients
with heart rhythm disorders
is essentially the opposite of
a low-carb diet, centered on
a day-to-day basis around fruits,
vegetables, grains, beans,
and nuts, with seafood at
most a few days a week;
eggs, dairy, and chicken on
more like a once-a-week basis;
and other meat on more like
a once-a-month basis, in part
because we're trying to cut down
on saturated and trans fats.
Whole-food plant-based diets
emphasizing whole grains,
legumes (beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils),
vegetables, fruits and nuts
and excluding most (or all) animal
products may play a special role,
as they not only maximize
protective foods,
but also exclude potentially
harmful animal foods.
For example, there is persuasive
evidence that avoidance
of certain foods may beneficially
affect atrial fibrillation,
such as the avoidance
of dark fish and alcohol.
The dark fish thing comes from
the Framingham Heart Study.
By dark fish, they mean
salmon, swordfish, bluefish,
mackerel, and sardines.
And they found in an exploratory
analysis that those participants
who consumed more than
4 servings of darkfish
like salmon or sardines a week
were at a whopping
6-fold higher risk of
developing Afib, though
the intake of fish in general
didn't seem to have any effect.
We're not exactly sure why
alcohol is so bad when
it comes to arrhythmias,
but we might have as
much as an 8% increase
in the relative risk of Afib
associated with each drink
one might have per day,
though drinking coffee or caffeine
in general does not seem
to be related to arrhythmia risk.
Where plant-based diets
really shine, though,
is in Afib risk factor management.
Plant-based diets may
reduce the likelihood of many
traditional risk factors that are
associated with Afib, including
hypertension, hyperthyroidism,
obesity, and diabetes.
High blood pressure is one
of the major risk factors,
accounting for about one-fifth
of all new cases of Afib,
which is where plant-based
diets can come in:
improving vasodilation, the ability
for your arteries to expand naturally,
in addition to the anti-inflammatory
and antioxidant effects, and
increased potassium intake,
and decreased blood
viscosity or sludginess.
In terms of hyperthyroidism,
excluding all animal foods
from one's diet was associated
with half the prevalence
of hyperthyroidism compared
with those who eat meat,
with vegetarians and
fish-only diets associated
with intermediate protection.
Having excess body fat may
be responsible for about
another fifth of all Afib cases.
But the good news is significantÂ
weight loss is associated
with a 6-fold greater freedom
from atrial fibrillation.
You can see that those with Afib
who started out overweight, but
lost 10% or more of
their body weight,
5 years later only 10%
ended up with Afib,
whereas those who lost less
than 3% or gained weight,
60% ended up with Afib,
6 times more.
Here are all the atrial fibrillation
risk factors that can be prevented,
arrested or even reversed with a
healthy enough plant-based diet:
high blood pressure, type 2
diabetes, obesity, systemic
inflammation, and heart disease.
In light of these findings,
dietary modifications are
of paramount importance.
But you don't know if it could
actually cure atrial fibrillation
until you put it to the test.
Unfortunately, all we
have are case reports,
but this one is quite compelling.
An 82-year-old man
presents with polypharmacy,
meaning on a bunch of
different medications due to
coronary artery disease,
a heart attack history,
ischemic cardiomyopathy,
high cholesterol,
high blood pressure, and
persistent atrial fibrillation, who
presented with memory loss, cognitive
impairment, fatigue and weakness.
Now, if you're not going to change
the diet and lifestyle that led to all
the problems in the first place,
then drugs can certainly be
better than nothing.
Yet commonly used blood pressure
and cholesterol-lowering
medications provide actually
little absolute risk reduction
and pose significant risk of adverse
effects, as I've explored before.
So this guy decided to start
treating the underlying cause.
So he started a whole-food
plant-based diet with moderate
physical activity, resulting in a rapid
reduction of high cholesterol
and high blood pressure,
and the discontinuation
of statin, antihypertensive,
and beta blocker drug therapy.
The patient also reported
reversal of impaired cognition
and symptoms associated
with atrial fibrillation
and ischemic cardiomyopathy,
including light-headedness,
fatigue, and weakness.
Check out these numbers.
Started out on all his medications.
Started eating healthier in February
and his LDL bad cholesterol
dropped 37% down to 72.
And you say, yeah, but he's still on
cholesterol-lowering statin drugs.
But even after his doctor discontinued
it, and his blood pressure meds,
his cholesterol stayed down,
and his blood pressure
completely normalized.
OK, but what happened
to his atrial fibrillation?
Completely resolved.
Here's how the patient described it.
"In December 2017, I suffered
a near-fatal heart attack
and was rushed to the hospital.
I immediately had a stent put in.
The following day,
I was prescribed a number of
drugs to manage my condition.
My brain fog got worse
and I felt tired all the time.
I decided enough was enough.
I had already lost four years of my life
to medication-induced brain fog;
I wasn't going to sacrifice more.
I had been eating a wholesome
Mediterranean diet,
but I was then educated on the
benefits of cutting out all the crap.
And now? I have the strength
to lift weights and walk
and run on the treadmill
an hour every day.
I feel more alive
than I have for years.
I wake up each morning with
a clear head and happy heart,
grateful to not have to
take a handful of drugs.
Even though I'm not perfect
with my diet, I've seen huge
benefits from eating this way.
My blood tests have shown
remarkable improvement,
which keeps me motivated
to stay on track.
Because of my improvement,
my cardiologist suggested
I could let go of his
last remaining drug.
Eating this food gave me an
opportunity to reclaim my health.
In our next story,
we look at how fish
and fish oil consumption
do not appear to protect
against heart disease,
arrhythmias,
or sudden death.
So why would they
increase cancer risk?
2013 was a bad year for fish oil.
Claims were crushed that
the long chain omega 3's
in fish oil, EPA, and DHA would stop
the progression of heart disease.
And then DHA was associated with
increased risk of prostate cancer,
and monumentally failed
to treat macular degeneration.
This over-the-top rhetoric
sounded a little suspicious
and indeed the paper was retracted
because the author sells some
rival supplement that he failed to
disclose, but he does have a point.
I covered the fish oil
failure for heart disease.
What about the
increased cancer risk?
Men with the highest
circulating levels in their blood
of the long chain
omega 3 fat DHA
were found to be at higher
risk for prostate cancer,
though a subsequent compilation
of all such studies suggested EPA,
the other major long chain
omega 3 in fish and fish oil
may be more closely associated
with increased cancer risk.
Either way, these long chain
omega 3's have been promoted
for prevention of heart
disease and cancer,
but now that we know that not
only does there appear to be
no benefit for death,
heart attack, or stroke,
but that there may be an
elevation in cancer risk,
the general recommendation to
increase the intake of these fats
should consider
its potential risks.
How could eating more fish
or fish oil increase cancer risk?
Well, there are some industrial
pollutants like PCBs linked
to increased prostate cancer risk,
and the primary source of exposure
in the general population is
believed to be through diet
from fish, meat, and
dairy products.
If you do a supermarket survey,
the PCBs, shown in white here,
are highest in freshwater fish, and
lowest in vegans — cannibals take note.
No, that's just how they label the
market basket of plant foods,
though vegans have been tested and
were found to be significantly
less polluted, including the PCB
specifically linked to prostate cancer.
And so maybe the confounding factor
was meat consumption in general,
not just fish, and that lower meat
consumption may be a reason
for the lower rates of prostate
cancer in the lower DHA group,
as the consumption of well-done meat
is associated with an increased risk
of prostate cancer and
intake should be restricted.
We also used to think omega 3's
could protect us from arrhythmias —
abnormal heart rhythms
like atrial fibrillation.
Millions suffer from the condition,
which causes an irregular heartbeat
and a higher risk
of stroke and death,
but fish and fish oil consumption
does not appear effective
for preventing it
or treating it.
Other arrhythmias can be life
threatening and cause sudden death.
Despite initial encouraging
results, more recent studies
have not only failed to reduce sudden
cardiac death with omega 3's,
but actually increased
mortality in cardiac patients.
For example, men with heart disease
advised to eat more oily fish
or supplied with fish oil capsules
were found to have a higher risk
of cardiac death, maybe because of the
contaminants in fish such as mercury?
In either case, given the inconsistent
benefits and the potential adverse
effects, omega 3's
must be prescribed
with caution and generalized
recommendations to increase
fish intake or to take fish oil capsules
need to be reconsidered.
Finally today,
did you know that a cup a day
of beans, chickpeas, or lentils
for three months may
slow resting heart rate
as much as exercising for
50 hours on a treadmill?
The accumulated weight
of evidence linking
elevated resting heart rate
to a shortened lifespan—
even in apparently
healthy individuals,
makes a strong case for
it to be considered
in the assessment
of risk.
It’s got strong advantages.
Taking one’s pulse
is cheap,
takes little time,
it’s understandable
to people,
and it’s something
everyone can do at home
to measure their progress to
become an active participant
in their own
health management.
Every ten beats
per minute increase
is associated with
a 10 to 20% increase
in the risk of death.
There seems to be a
continuous increase in risk
with increasing
heart rate,
at least for values above
about a beat a second.
So we can just look
at our watch
and if our heart is beating faster
than the seconds go by—
even when we’re
sitting quietly,
then we have to do
something about it,
especially when we start
getting up around 80 or 90.
Men with no apparent
heart disease evidence
with a pulse of 90 may
have five times higher risk
of sudden cardiac death—
meaning their first symptom
is their last—
compared to those down
the safety zone.
Living up around 90 increases
heart disease risk
at a level similar
to smoking.
If you ask most doctors, though,
90 is considered normal.
The accepted limits of heartrate
have long been set
at 60 and 100 beats/min.
How did they come
up with that?
It was adopted as a
matter of convenience
just based on the scale of
the squares on EKG paper.
A historical accident like
the QWERTY keyboard
that just became the norm.
60 to 100 doesn’t even
represent the bell curve.
These cardiologists measured
the heart rate of 500 people
and concluded that
45 to 95 was a better
definition of normal,
rounding to 50 to 90,
which a survey of leading
cardiologists concurred with.
Now we know that normal
doesn’t necessarily mean optimal,
but doctors shouldn’t be
telling people with heart rates
in the 50’s that they're
are too low;
in fact they may be right
where they should be.
Certainly a heart rate
higher than 80
should ring an alarm bell,
but what can we
do about it?
Exercise is one
obvious possibility.
Ironically, you make
the heart go faster
so that that the
rest of the time
your heart beats slower.
The public health benefits
of physical exercise,
especially for heart protection,
are widely accepted,
and among the many biological
mechanisms proposed
to account for this
risk-reducing effect
is autonomic nervous system
regulation of the heart.
That’s your brain’s
ability to slow down
the resting beat
of our heart.
If you put people through
a 12 week aerobic
conditioning program
of cycling, stairmaster,
and running on
a treadmill,
you can drop their
resting heart rate down
from about 69
to about 66,
so three beats
per minute drop.
Of course you have
to keep it up;
stop exercising and your
resting heart rate
goes right back up.
Exercise is just one way
to drop our heartrate, though.
The way to our heart may also
be through our stomach.
What if instead of
three months of exercise,
you did three months
of beans?
A cup a day of beans,
chickpeas, or lentils.
The first randomized
controlled trial of beans
for the treatment
of diabetes.
And indeed successfully
improved blood sugar control
dropping A1C levels
from 7.4 to 6.9,
but this was also
the first study
to ever assess the effect
of bean consumption
on heart rate.
And indeed one of the few
to determine the effect
on heartrate of any
dietary intervention.
This is particularly important
in diabetics
since having a higher
resting heart rate
not only increases the
risk of death
just like everybody else,
but also appears to
predict greater risk
of diabetic complications,
such as damage to the
nerves and eyes.
So how did beans do?
A 3.4 beat drop
in heartrate—
just as much as the 250 hours
on a treadmill.
We’re not sure why beans
are as powerful as exercise
in bringing down one’s
resting heart rate.
In addition to the potential
direct beneficial effects
of all the good stuff
in legumes,
there is also the potential
displacement value
of reducing some of
the animal protein foods
by eating so
many beans instead.
Regardless, we should consider
eating pulses for our pulse.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.